Finding Aid for Richard C. Van Dusen Papers 1954-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Richard C. Van Dusen Papers 1954-1972
Van Dusen, Richard C. (Richard Campbell), 1925-
State Republican politician, aide and political advisor to George Romney, legal advisor to the governor and later undersecretary of Housing and Urban Development. Material concerning his campaign for the state attorney general's office in 1956, the elections of 1960, 1962, 1964, and 1968, and the state constitutional convention, 1961-1963; and files detailing his career in Washington at HUD.
85527 Aa 2
9 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mr. Van Dusen (donor no. 6350 ) and came to the library in 1979.
The collection is open for research.
Richard C. Van Dusen was born on July 18, 1925 in Jackson, Michigan. In 1943 he graduated from Deerfield Academy, Deerfield, Massachusetts, and, having joined the US Navy V-12 program, was assigned to college training at Central Michigan University. In February 1944 he was transferred to the Naval ROTC program at the University of Minnesota. Graduating in October 1945 he served on several ships in the navy's Seventh Fleet in the Pacific area.
In June 1946 he was released from active duty. In October he entered the Harvard Law School, from which he received an LL.B. in May 1949. Returning to Michigan, Van Dusen joined the Detroit law firm of Dickinson, Wright, Davis, McKean & Cudlip, a firm heavily involved in corporate law. Van Dusen remains associated with this firm, now known as Dickinson, Wright, Moon, Van Dusen & Freeman, although his work with it has been interrupted several times to serve in posts of public trust.
Republican politics ran in Van Dusen's family. His maternal grandfather, W.B. Campbell, served as a Republican state legislator. Van Dusen, too, was attracted to partisan political activity. He began working within the Michigan Republican party soon after his graduation from Harvard. By 1952 Van Dusen had become chairman of the Birmingham Republican Club and chairman of the third legislative district Republican Committee.
In 1954 Van Dusen successfully sought elected office, becoming the representative of the State House's twenty second district. In 1956 he ran for state attorney general, but was defeated along with the other Republican statewide candidates.
His defeat led Van Dusen back into full-time private legal practice, supplemented briefly by teaching a course at Detroit College of Law. Van Dusen continued to be interested in politics, however. In 1960 he served as Vice Chairman of Michigan Volunteers for Nixon. He was elected as a delegate to the state constitutional convention of 1961-1962, where he served as Chairman of the Committee on Rules and Resolutions, and as a member of the Committee on Taxation.
Van Dusen's role in con-con was paralleled by his involvement with the political career of George Romney. Van Dusen served first as an advisor to Romney in the 1962 gubernatorial campaign. At the campaign's successful conclusion Van Dusen acted as a special assistant to the governor-elect and then as legal advisor to the governor.
In 1964 Van Dusen returned to private legal practice, but he remained a member of the Romney inner circle. He was a key advisor in the Romney presidential campaign of 1966-1968, and served under Romney as an undersecretary of Housing and Urban Development from 1969 to 1973. After leaving Washington, Van Dusen resumed private legal practice.
The papers of Richard Van Dusen reflect his public career and his close involvement with George Romney. The papers divide themselves into two series. Political and Legislative Files relates to his own political career and to his association with state Republican party politics and his relationship with Governor George Romney. The other series concerns his work with Romney within the US Department of Housing and Urban Development.
Subjects:
Elections--Michigan--1956.; Elections--Michigan--1960.; Elections--Michigan--1962.; Elections--Michigan--1964.; Elections--Michigan--1968.; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Republican Party (Mich.); Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; United States. Dept. of Housing and Urban Development.; Van Dusen, Richard C. (Richard Campbell), 1925-1991
- Political and legislative file
  The Political and Legislative Files can be divided into four subseries: Chronological, George Romney, Political Lawsuits, and Constitutional Convention.
  - Biography (Box 1)
  - Chronological file
    The chronological files contain all materials relating to Van Dusen's legislative career and to his unsuccessful campaign for attorney general. There is also a large body of material relating to the 1960 Nixon presidential campaign in Michigan. Finally there is material relating to the platform committee of the 1964 Republican National Convention, of which Van Dusen was a member.
    - 1954 General, 8 folders (Box 1)
    - 1955
      - General, 11 folders (Box 1)
      - Health Agency (Box 1)
      - Tax Legislation (Box 1)
    - 1956
      - Attorney General campaign
        - Calendar (Box 1)
        - Campaign (Box 1)
        - Diary (Box 1)
        - General, 7 folders (Box 1)
        - Nomination (Box 1)
        - Speeches (Box 1)
      - General January-July 1956, 7 folders (Box 1)
      - General September-December 1956, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - House of Representatives (Box 2)
      - Unemployment Compensation (Box 2)
      - State Convention May 1956, September 1956, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1957
      - General, 5 folders (Box 2)
      - Republican Discussion Group (Box 2)
      - Republican Legislative Liaison Committee (Box 2)
    - 1958
      - General, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - Republican Discussion Group (Box 2)
      - State Convention Platform Committee, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1959
      - General (Box 2)
      - Republican Discussion Group (Box 2)
    - 1960
      - Fieldmen October 1960 (Box 2)
      - General, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Michigan Volunteers for Nixon
        - Eighteenth Congressional District plans (Box 2)
        - Finance Committee June-December 1960, 4 folders (Box 2)
        - General January-October 1960, 6 folders (Box 2)
        - Memos (Box 3)
        - Washington office (Box 3)
      - Republican Discussion Group (Box 3)
    - 1961
      - General (Box 3)
      - Michigan Volunteers for Nixon-Finance Committee (Box 3)
    - 1962 General (Box 3)
    - 1963 General (Box 3)
    - 1964
      - General, 9 folders (Box 3)
      - National Convention
        - General, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - Platform Committee
          - Correspondence (Box 3)
          - Drafts, 2 folders (Box 3)
          - Jack Tar (Box 3)
      - Republican Citizens' Committee (Box 3)
    - 1965
      - Fundraising (Box 3)
      - General, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Task Force on Programs and Goals (Box 3)
    - 1966
      - General (Box 3)
      - Opinions re. Apportioning delegates (Box 3)
      - United Republican Fund (Box 3)
    - 1967 General (Box 3)
    - 1968
      - General (Box 3)
      - National Convention (Box 3)
    - 1969 Republican National Convention (Box 3)
    - 1970 Republican National Committee (Box 4)
    - 1971 Republican National Committee (Box 4)
    - 1972 Republican National Committee (Box 4)
  - George Romney file
    The George Romney subseries deals extensively with Romney's first gubernatorial campaign, and his first year in office. It also concerns Romney's presidential campaign.
    - 1962
      - Election Campaign
        - General, 13 folders (Box 4)
        - Negro activities (Box 4)
        - Plans and organization (Box 4)
        - Research papers, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Romney-Swainson TV debate, 4 folders (Box 4)
      - John Birch Society (Box 4)
      - Special assistant to the governor elect
        - General November-December, 3 folders (Box 4)
        - Organization of executive office (Box 4)
    - 1963
      - Correspondence [A-D], 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Correspondence [E-Z], 7 folders (Box 5)
      - Employment information (Civil Service) (Box 5)
      - General (Box 5)
    - 1964
      - City income tax bill (Box 5)
      - General, 6 folders (Box 5)
    - 1965 General, 5 folders (Box 5)
    - 1966
      - Eligibility of Romney for presidency (Box 5)
      - Fundraising, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - General, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Republican Governors' Conference December 9-10, 1966 (Box 5)
      - Scheduling (Box 5)
    - 1967
      - College Americans for Romney (Box 5)
      - Coordinating Committee (Box 5)
      - Eligibility of Romney for presidency
        - General, 4 folders (Box 5)
        - Congressional Record (Box 5)
        - Printed, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Fundraising, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Issues (Box 6)
      - Resource People (Box 6)
      - Romney Ambassadors (Box 6)
      - Romney Associates (Box 6)
      - Scheduling
        - General, 4 folders (Box 6)
        - European trip (Box 6)
      - Speech and Research, 5 folders (Box 6)
      - Tax Studies, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Teen age Republicans of New York State (Box 6)
      - Urban Tour reports
        - Chicago (Box 6)
        - Detroit (Box 6)
        - Indianapolis (Box 6)
        - New York (Box 6)
        - Rochester (Box 6)
        - St. Louis (Box 6)
        - Vienna, Ohio (Box 6)
        - Washington, D.C. (Box 6)
    - 1968
      - Eligibility of Romney for Presidency (Box 6)
      - Fundraising (Box 6)
      - General, 6 folders (Box 6)
      - G.P. Putnam & Sons (Box 6)
      - Speech and Research, 4 folders (Box 6)
      - Tax Studies (Box 6)
  - Political Lawsuits file
    Most interesting among the Political Lawsuits subseries is the documentation and testimony regarding Durant v. Stahlin et al. Richard Durant, a Goldwater conservative and one time member of the John Birch Society, chaired the Fourteenth Congressional district Republican Party. Relations between Romney and Durant were always poor. Eventually they degenerated to the point that Durant sued Romney and several of his aides for libel.
    - Kelly v. Van Dusen 1962, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Durant v. Stahlin et al.
      - 1962 (Box 7)
      - 1963, 8 folders (Box 7)
      - 1964 (Box 7)
      - 1965, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - 1966 (Box 7)
      - Printed Testimony and Appeals, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Constitutional Convention File
    Although much of the materials found within the Constitutional Convention subseries is relatively routine, there is information relating to the campaign to call the convention, especially the activities of the Citizens for Michigan organization headed by then automobile executive George Romney.
    - 1960 Citizens for Michigan (Box 7)
    - 1961
      - Campaign correspondence (Box 7)
      - Campaign plans (Box 7)
      - General April-June 1961, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - General July-September 1961, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Inquiries (Box 8)
      - Nominating petitions (Box 8)
    - 1962
      - Citizens for Michigan (Box 8)
      - General, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Nisbet v. Hare
        - Correspondence (Box 8)
        - Legal documents, 4 folders (Box 8)
        - Memo of May 8, 1962 (Box 8)
    - Undated (Box 8)
- Undersecretary of Housing and Urban Development
  The Undersecretary of Housing and Urban Development series consists exclusively of carbon copies of Van Dusen's outgoing correspondence. The earliest material seems to have been kept by Van Dusen himself, the latter in a file kept by another person. Both files, however, consist solely of Van Dusen's own correspondence.
  - Van Dusen File
    - 1969, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - 1970
      - January-June 1970 (Box 8)
      - July-December 1970 (Box 9)
    - 1971
      - January-June 1971 (Box 9)
      - July-August 1971 (Box 9)
  - Bowman file
    - 1969, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - 1970 (Box 9)
    - 1971, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - 1972, 2 folders (Box 9)